Finding Aid for the Slee Visiting Professor in Music Papers, 1957-1993
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
Slee Visiting Professor in Music Papers, 1957-1993
Mus. Arc. 72
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Department
1 box (33 folders)
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
The collection chiefly consists of correspondence between thirty-two composers being considered or invited to fill the position of Slee Visiting Professor in Music at the State University of New York at Buffalo. It also contains clippings pertaining to the composers.
Administrative Information
Terms of Access
Materials can be examined by qualified researchers in the Music Library during hours of operation during which Music Librarians are present. In order to insure access, researchers are advised to contact the Music Library in advance of visits.
Acquisition Information
Gift of State University of New York at Buffalo Music Department.
Accruals and Additions
No further accruals are expected to this collection.
Alternate Forms
The collection only contains photocopies. The original documents are held by University Archives at the University at Buffalo.
Biographical Note
The position of Slee Visiting Professor in Music at the University at Buffalo was funded by Frederick Caldecott Slee. Slee (1870-1954) was a corporate lawyer in Buffalo who was also a talented amateur musician who composed and played viola. He and his wife, Alice MacDonald Slee, funded through their estates two major musical events at the University at Buffalo: the annual performance of the complete cycle of Beethoven's string quartets by some of the world's leading string quartet ensembles, and a visiting position in the Music Department to be filled by a leading composer or music theorist of the day. The Slee Visiting Professors presented lectures and recitals of music selected by them. This series of lecture-recitals occurred from 1957 to 1975. The fund was later shifted to be used for a Slee Chair position in music theory within the department rather than funding visiting faculty.
Scope and Content Note
The collection chiefly consists of correspondence between thirty-two composers being considered or invited to fill the position of Slee Visiting Professor in Music at the State University of New York at Buffalo. It also contains clippings pertaining to the composers. The folder of correspondence concerning Aaron Copland, who was appointed the first Slee Visting Professor in Music in 1957, is especially noteworthy due to the controversy caused by accusations that he was affiliated with the Communist Party.
Arrangement
The collection is in one series arranged alphabetically by the composers' surnames.
Container List
- Lists and articles 1960-1993, 8 items (Box 1, Item 01)
  1 leaf, January 24 1976 Buffalo Evening News article about Frederick and Alice Slee's funding of the annual Beethoven string quartet cycle
  1 leaf, list of Slee Professors at the University at Buffalo Music Department, 1957-1975
  1 leaf, January 17 1960 list of composers contacted regarding the Slee Professorship
  1 leaf, 1967-1968, Possible candidates for Slee Chair
  2 leaves, October 17 1960, from Allen Giles inviting unnamed composer to become the Slee Professorship
  1 leaf, December 2 1974 from Terry Charles Schwarz to publisher W. W. Norton concerning inaccuracies about the Slee gift in Philip Hart's Orpheus in the New World
  3 leaves, March 1 1967 from Joel Spiegelman to Vladimir Prokofieff
  2 leaves, January 27 1993 concert announcement for program including music by Slee Professors
- Barber, Samuel, 1910-1981 10 November 1960, 1 item (Box 1, Item 02)
  1 manuscript leaf, November 10 1960, from Barber to Allen Giles
- Berger, Arthur, 1912-2003 1 November 1960, 1 item (Box 1, Item 03)
  2 typescript leaves, November 1 1960, from Berger to Allen Giles
- Britten, Benjamin, 1913-1976 25 October 1960, 1 item (Box 1, Item 04)
  1 typescript leaf, October 25 1960, written by J. W. Cullum on behalf of Britten to Allen Giles
- Carter, Elliott, 1908-2012 1960-1962, 3 items (Box 1, Item 05)
  1 typescript leaf, November 3 1960, from Carter to Allen Giles
  1 typescript leaf, June 22, 1962, from Carter to Allen Sapp
  1 typescript transcription of cablegram sent to Elliott Carter, June 19, 1962, from Allen Sapp
- Chávez, Carlos, 1899-1978 19 July 1957, 12 August 1957, 4 items (Box 1, Item 06)
  2 typescript leaves, July 19 1957, from Chávez to Cameron Baird
  2 typescript leaves, August 12 1957, from Chávez to Cameron Baird
  2 clippings about performances of Chávez's music
- Copland, Aaron, 1900-1990 14 January 1957-June 1957, 17 items; Content from this folder related to accusations about Copland's alleged ties to Communism can also be found in digital form within the summary (see pages 33 and following)of the Music Library's exhibition, Cameron Baird: Bringing Paul Hindemith and Aaron Copland to Buffalo (Box 1, Item 07)
  1 typescript leaf, January 14 1957, from Copland to Cameron Baird
  2 manuscript leaves, January 27 1957, from Copland to Cameron Baird
  1 typescript leaf, February 5 1957, from W. L. Barnette (Les) to Cameron Baird
  2 typescript leaves, February 5 1957, from Cameron Baird to Joseph McNamara
  1 typescript leaf, February 8 1957, from Joseph McNamara to Cameron Baird
  2 typescript leaves, February 11 1957, from Copland to Cameron Baird
  1 typescript leaf, February 26 1957, from Cameron Baird to Joseph McNamara
  1 typescript leaf, April 5 1957, from Copland to Cameron Baird
  2 typescript leaves, with manuscript notes on verso, April 23 1957, from Copland to Cameron Baird
  2 manuscript leaves, June 1 1957, from Copland to Cameron Baird
  1 manuscript leaf, Friday (June 1957), from Copland to Cameron Baird
  1 Addendum for summer catalog and for summer music brochure 1957, from Cameron Baird
  5 clippings
- Cowell, Henry, 1897-1965 1960-1963, 3 items (Box 1, Item 08)
  1 typescript leaf, October 27 1960, from Cowell to Allen Giles
  1 typescript leaf, December? 17 1960, from Cowell to Allen Giles
  1 typescript leaf, July 17 1963, from Cowell to Norma Sapp (not related to lectureship)
- Creston, Paul, 1906-1985 10 November 1960, 1 item (Box 1, Item 09)
  1 typescript leaf, November 10 1960, from Creston to Allen Giles
- Dallapiccola, Luigi, 1904-1975 June 1962, 2 items (Box 1, Item 10)
  1 telegram, June 11 1962, from Allen Sapp to Dallapiccola
  1 telegram, June 16 1962, from Dallapiccola to Allen Sapp
- Dello Joio, Norman, 1913-2008 28 October 1960, 1 item (Box 1, Item 11)
  1 manuscript leaf, October 28 1960, from Dello Joio to Allen Giles
- Diamond, David, 1915-2005 1960-1963, 3 items (Box 1, Item 12)
  1 cablegram, November 7 1960, from Allen Giles to Diamond
  1 cablegram, November 8 1960, from Diamond to Allen Giles
  1 program flyer for Diamond lecture-concerts, 1963, University at Buffalo
- Feldman, Morton, 1926-1987 undated, 6 items (Box 1, Item 13)
  6 clippings about Feldman, originally sent to Allen Sapp by Lukas Foss
- Fine, Irving, 1914-1962 2 November 1960, 1 item (Box 1, Item 14)
  2 typescript leaves, November 2 1960, from Fine to Allen Giles
- Foss, Lukas, 1922-2009 1960-1964, 6 items (Box 1, Item 15)
  2 manuscript leaves, October 31 1960, from Foss to Allen Giles
  2 typescript leaves, December 5 1960, unsigned, on Music Department letterhead to Foss
  1 typescript leaf, May 15 1961, from Milton Albrecht to Foss
  1 typescript leaf, June 8 1961, from Milton Albrecht to Foss
  1 typescript leaf, June 13 1961, from Foss to Milton Albrecht
  1 typescript leaf, July 14 1964, from Foss to Allen Sapp
- Haieff, Alexei, 1914-1994 1961-1966, 14 items (Box 1, Item 16)
  14 leaves (manuscript and typescript), July 24 1961- July 12 1966, to and from Haieff, and additional correspondence concerning Haieff
- Harris, Roy, 1898-1979 1960, 1 item (Box 1, Item 17)
  3 manuscript leaves, 1960, from Harris to Allen Giles
- Harrison, Lou, 1917-2003 October 1961, 2 items (Box 1, Item 18)
  1 manuscript leaf, October 8 1961, from Harrison to Allen Sapp
  1 typescript leaf, October 26 1961, from Allen Sapp to Harrison
- Kirchner, Leon 11 June 1964, undated, 2 items (Box 1, Item 19)
  1 typescript leaf, June 11 1964, from Allen Sapp to Kirchner
  1 manuscript leaf, undated, unsigned, probably internal memo to Allen Sapp about Kirchner
- Lees, Benjamin, 1924-2010 1961-1963, 5 items (Box 1, Item 20)
  1 typescript leaf, July 16 1961, from Lees to Allen Sapp
  1 typescript leaf, July 26 1961, from Allen Sapp to Lees
  1 typescript leaf, Sept. 29 1961, from Lees to Allen Sapp
  1 typescript leaf, March 8 1963, from Lees to Allen Sapp
  1 typescript leaf, March 13 1963, from Allen Sapp to Lees
- Lutosławski, Witold, 1913-1994 May-June 1964, 5 items (Box 1, Item 21)
  1 typescript leaf, May 6 1964, from Lutosławski to Allen Sapp
  1 typescript leaf, May 21 1964, to Allen Sapp from "Bob" regarding Lutosławski
  1 typescript leaf, May 26 1964, text of cablegram from Allen Sapp to Lutosławski
  1 cablegram, May 26 1964, from Allen Sapp to Lutosławski
  1 typescript leaf, June 25 1964, from Allen Sapp to Lutosławski
- Milhaud, Darius, 1892-1974 1960-1964, 3 items (Box 1, Item 22)
  1 manuscript leaf, October 28 [1960?], from Milhaud to Allen Giles
  1 telegram, January 21 1964, from Allen Sapp to Milhaud
  1 manuscript leaf, January 21 1964, from Milhaud to Allen Sapp
- Panufnik, Andrzej, 1914-1991 circa 1960, 1 folder (Box 1, Item 23)
  14 leaves of promotional material from Arthur Judson, Columbia Artists Management
- Persichetti, Vincent, 1915-1987 29 October 1960, 1 item (Box 1, Item 24)
  1 manuscript leaf, October 29 1960, from Persichetti to Allen Giles
- Piston, Walter, 1894-1976 1 November 1960, 1 item (Box 1, Item 25)
  1 manuscript leaf, November 1 1960, from Piston to Allen Giles
- Plamenac, Dragan, 1895-1983 14 February 1968, 1 item (Box 1, Item 26)
  1 typescript leaf, February 14 1968, from Plamenac to Allen Sapp
- Porter, Quincy, 1897-1966 25 October 1960, 1 item (Box 1, Item 27)
  1 typescript leaf, October 25 1960, from Porter to Allen Giles
- Poulenc, Francis, 1899-1963 2 November 1960, 1 item (Box 1, Item 28)
  1 manuscript leaf, November 2 1960, from Poulenc to unnamed correspondent
- Powell, Mel 27 April 1967, 1 item (Box 1, Item 29)
  1 telegram, April 27 1967, from Allen Sapp to Powell with 1 typescript leaf transcription of text
- Rorem, Ned, 1923- 3 July 1962, undated, 2 items (Box 1, Item 30)
  1 typescript leaf, July 3 1962, from Rorem to Allen Sapp
  1 typescript leaf, undated, of Rorem's recommendations of composers for the Slee Lectures
- Stockhausen, Karlheinz, 1928-2007 1964, 1 item (Box 1, Item 31)
  5 typescript leaves from Music Dept., University of Pennsylvania, announcing Stockhausen's appointment to teach composition Spring 1964
- Thompson, Randall, 1899-1984 3 November 1960, 1 item (Box 1, Item 32)
  1 manuscript leaf, November 3 1960, from Thompson to Allen Giles
- Wolpe, Stefan September 1968, 2 items (Box 1, Item 33)
  1 typescript leaf, September 18 1968, from Josef Marx on behalf of Stefan Wolpe to Allen Sapp
  1 typescript leaf, September 26 1968, from Esther Swartz on behalf of Allen Sapp to Josef Marx
Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog.
Contributors
Giles, Allen; Sapp, Allen, 1922-1999
Subjects
Copland, Aaron, 1900-1990--Correspondence; Composers--Correspondence; State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Department
Genres
Correspondence; Clippings
Associated Material
Related Resources
Related Resources in the Music Library
Slee Lecture Recitals Inventory
Inventory of lectures and recitals presented by the Slee Visiting Professors in Music, 1957-1975.
Frederick and Alice Slee
Online exhibit about the lives of Frederick and Alice Slee, with examples of Frederick Slee's prose and musical writing and information about the Beethoven quartet cycle funded by the Slees.